Today's דף daf is פ"ו Pei Vav and we begin on the
bottom of פ"ה ע"ב. Pei Hei Amud Bet.
And we pick up with where were we? והתנן, vehatnan, I'm sorry,
not that. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel,
second wide line. And we are talking about where one can place
the עירוב eruv and where one can place the שיתוף shituf or
שיתופי מבואות. shitufai mevo'ot. So the עירוב eruv is placed in a
בית bayit in the חצר chatzer and the discussion in the משנה
mishnah is what constitutes a בית, bayit, what type of place fit
for living, and according to the opinion in the משנה, mishnah, the
תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, which is not debated in this משנה, mishnah,
that even a barn or place, a storage shed, presumably even if
nobody is living there, it's considered to be a place of habitation
because it's, you know, because it's a connection to a home.
Anyway, so it has to be a place of habitation, and for
the שיתוף, shituf, that can be in a חצר, chatzer, doesn't have
to be in a בית. bayit. Actually, according to תוספות, Tosafot, to
distinguish it from an עירוב, eruv, it shouldn't be in a house
or it can't be in a house, but certainly it doesn't have
to be. So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל בני חבורה
שהיו מסובין,
Amar Rav Yehuda Amar
Shmuel bnei chaburah she-hayu mesubin, if people, you know, there was a
group of people that they were all reclining, meaning having a nice
meal on Friday afternoon, וקדש עליהם היום, vekadesh aleihem hayom,
and it became שבת, Shabbos,
and they forgot to make an עירוב. eruv. פת שעל השולחן סומכין
עליה משום עירוב. pat she-al hashulchan somchin aleha mishum eruv.
The bread that they're all eating, they're all sharing, that can constitute
their עירוב. eruv. Now what it sounds like is that it didn't
even mean, this gets to questions we raised before about ownership and
so on, does somebody have to be קונה koneh the פת pat
for everybody in the room? Does he have to do it לשם
עירוב? leshem eruv? It doesn't sound like that. It sounds like the
fact that they're all sharing the bread, that experience of in reality
sharing the bread is suffices even without it actually being owned by
all of them. The other interesting question is did they have to
designate for an עירוב? eruv? You might remember we had earlier משניות
mishnayot about that you happen to be in partnership with somebody in
a barrel of wine and things, scenarios of that nature that could
also be a substitute for an עירוב. eruv. So that's simply the
sense here is that automatically it counts as an עירוב eruv even
without transferring ownership, even without designating it as such. Yeah, as long
as all the members who need to be part of the עירוב
eruv are part of this meal. ואמרי לה משום שיתוף, ve'amri lah
mishum shituf,
and some say that it counts to serve as the purposes of
a שיתוף shituf for the courtyard. אמר רבא ולא פליגי, Amar Rava
velo pligi, we're not debating. כאן במסובין בבית כאן במסובין בחצר. kan
bimesubin bebayit kan bimesubin bachatzer.
It depends if they're having a meal inside the בית bayit or
they're having a picnic. If they're having a meal inside the בית,
bayit, then it can count as an עירוב eruv because as we
said, the עירוב eruv has to be placed inside of a בית.
bayit. If they're eating it out in the חצר, chatzer, then it
cannot count as an עירוב eruv because it's not in the בית,
bayit, but it can count as a שיתוף shituf for the מבוי.
mavoi.
So even though it was just one person's bread, let's say he
invited them all over. That's what I said.
It sounds like the fact that in practice they're all sharing it
is sufficient and obviates need for actual joint ownership. The reality is
that they're actually all sharing it. Of course, didn't we require
like you have to have a whole loaf in front of them?
Didn't we require that?
That's an interesting point. Does it require that they have the whole
loaf? We
according to the opinion that you need דוקא davka bread and you
need a whole loaf of bread. But they started שבת? Shabbos?
Well no, they started eating from before שבת. Shabbos. No, but because
like you
know, they make קידוש Kiddush then it was שבת Shabbos and they
started eating?
No no, it says היו מסובין וקדש עליהם היום. hayu mesubin vekadesh
aleihem hayom.
So yeah, that's an interesting question.
I don't know, that's an interesting question. Would the fact that it
had started as a whole loaf be sufficient? Because normally you go
by where it is when שבת Shabbos begins.
I don't know, maybe this is assuming the position that you don't
need a whole loaf. It'd be interesting. I'd have to see how
this is brought down the הלכה. halakha. I didn't check because the
הלכה halakha we do rule the whole loaf idea. It's a good
question.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר אביי לרבא.
Amar Abaye le-Rava. So אביי Abaye said to
רבא. Rava. תניא דמסייע לך. tanya demasaye lach. A תניא tanya that
supports you, this idea about בית bayit and חצר chatzer which is
essentially also the thing you said at the end of yesterday. עירובי
חצירות בחצר ושיתופי מבואות במבוי. eiruvi chatzeirot bachatzer veshitufai mevo'ot bemavoi. So
an עירובי חצירות eiruvi chatzeirot you put in the חצר chatzer and
a שיתופי מבואות shitufai mevo'ot you put in the מבוי. mavoi. Now
that's a little bizarre because that sounds like it's actually in the
courtyard itself or in the street itself.
ובעינן בה ואכתי עירובי חצירות בחצר? uv'ainan bah ve'achti eiruvi chatzeirot bachatzer?
You put an עירובי חצירות eiruvi chatzeirot directly in the courtyard itself?
והתנן המניח את עירובו בבית שער אכסדרה ומרפסת אינו עירוב. vehatnan hamaniach
et eiruvo b'veit sh'ar achsadra u-mirpeset eino eruv. Our
משנה mishnah says that if you put it even in these, you
know, even in these sort of somewhat like
houses but spaces that are not domiciles, like you put it in
a gatehouse or a porch or whatever, it doesn't count as an
עירוב. eruv. So certainly it can't be in the courtyard itself. It
has to be in a
real בית. bayit. אלא אימא עירובי חצירות בבית שבחצר ושיתופי מבואות בחצר
שבמבוי. ela eima eiruvi chatzeirot bebayit shebachatzer veshitufai mevo'ot bachatzer shebamavoi. The
עירובי חצירות eiruvi chatzeirot goes in a בית bayit not in the
חצר chatzer but a בית bayit of the חצר chatzer and the
שיתופי מבואות shitufai mevo'ot goes in a חצר chatzer that feeds into
the מבוי. mavoi. into the alley into the street. So again it's
interesting just like we ended yesterday איתיביה דמסייע לך eitiviya demasaya lach
was actually the support was after you've amended the text. The actual
simple sense of the ברייתא braita contradicts the משנה mishna but after
you've amended the text now you're left with this support. So the
basic rule is an עירוב חצרות eruv chatzerot has to be in
a house that belongs to the חצר. chatzer. A, it has to
be a house, B, it has to belong to the חצר. chatzer.
It can't be a house of another חצר. chatzer. What constitutes a
house? It has to be a place certainly that minimally is fit
for living and dwelling, although what if it's a place like it's
you know a barn or a stable or something of that nature?
You don't live there but it's you know it's like a type
of it's
it's an edifice that sort of you know relates to your living
although you don't actually live there, that the משנה mishna seems to
say would be okay.
And so that's where the עירוב חצרות eruv chatzerot goes. Whether actually
there has to be an ongoing presence or whether you could be
even an absentee owner and if that's you know how that plays
out is not being discussed here. And then the other part is
that the שיתוף מבואות shituf mavo'ot can be in the is in
the חצר chatzer of the מבוי. mavoy. Does it—is it allowed to
be in a house? That's a debate of רש"י Rashi and תוספות.
Tosafot. רש"י Rashi says it's allowed to be in a house, but
תוספות Tosafot says no, it must be in the חצר שבמבוי chatzer
shebamavoy to distinguish it from the עירוב חצרות. eruv chatzerot. Okay so
that's the location of them. Parallel to the issue of the location
is the question of what type of a house is considered a
house that has to participate in the עירוב eruv and without participating
creates a problem. And that is a similar issue. There's a roughly
parallel although the other criteria there, which comes up in another גמרא,
Gemara, is the sense that there has to be an ongoing presence
of the owner of the house and actually that's something we're going
to be seeing in the next משנה. mishna. Okay now the גמרא
Gemara continues. רבי יהודה אומר אם יש שם תפיסת יד. Rabbi Yehuda
omer im yesh sham tfisat yad. As I said yesterday on שבת,
Shabbat, this הלכה halacha is actually extremely important הלכה למעשה. halacha lema'aseh.
He says this idea that if you have somebody dwelling in your,
you know, renting your barn or actually even living in your barn,
maybe not even living, whatever he is, that he's considered a new
presence in the courtyard and requires his participation in the עירוב, eruv,
that's only if you don't have a תפיסת יד, tfisat yad, like
a holding of a hand, in that in that barn. But if
you're keeping your equipment in that barn even if you've rented it
out to somebody else, it's still fundamentally considered your barn even though
he's the primary sort of inhabitant of it and therefore it's not
a separate domain and therefore does not require his participation in the
עירוב. eruv. And that is extremely important להלכה, lehalacha, as I mentioned
on שבת, Shabbat, because there are many times that you have a
city that doesn't have an עירוב eruv and the question is can
you carry in the apartment building? You know why not? It's surrounded
by walls. What the reason why not is is because that's an
exact a perfect application of a modern day עירוב חצרות. eruv chatzerot.
You have all these separate units that open up into a shared
space of the hallway, it should need an עירוב. eruv.
Similar questions come up I mentioned on like cruise ships, you know,
that they all have this shared space, it's all surrounded by walls
but they have individual cabins that open up into this shared space.
Or hotels maybe even a more common example. So in almost all
of those scenarios, the owner has some תפיסת יד tfisat yad in
each unit. Even in apartment buildings, you know, he might own the
major appliances. In hotels and in and in ships you don't have
really a right to this particular unit, if they wanted to they
could move you to another unit. And that is enough to really
say that they are not—that they're not separate units here. They're not
like separate ownerships because there's one person, the owner, who has a
תפיסת יד tfisat yad in all of the in you know in
all of those units. So that becomes extremely important להלכה lehalacha in
order for obviating the need of an עירוב חצרות eruv chatzerot in
many cases. So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. The
גמרא Gemara actually goes off on a bit of a tangent about
this because it's speaking about like—so let's take a look. היכי דמי
תפיסת יד? heichi dami tfisat yad? What's considered a תפיסת יד? tfisat
yad? כגון חצר של בונייס kegon chatzer shel Bunyas or של בן
בונייס. shel Ben Bunyas. Like the courtyard of Ben Bunyas, where רש"י
Rashi says who is this guy? He was very rich and he
would rent houses to everybody in the courtyard but he kept his
own like equipment, various objects of his in every single house. Okay
and therefore it would like he'd rent out a furnished apartment, not
unfurnished apartments and therefore he was had a תפיסת יד tfisat yad
in all of those units so they wouldn't have to make an
עירוב eruv because it would all be considered one person's one person's
units and not separate people. Okay now the גמרא Gemara has a
little digression. א בן בונייס אתא לקמיה דרבי. A Ben Bunyas ata
lekamei d'Rabbi. So Ben Bunyas, obviously this wealthy person, came in front
of רבי. Rabbi. אמר להו, amar lehu, he said to his like
servants, פנו מקום לבן מאה מנה. pnu makom l'ven me'ah maneh. Clear
out a place for this person who has a, you know, a
hundred מנה, maneh, very rich person. Okay. רבי Rabbi said to his
servants like you know like set the table make a nice place
you know get or רש"י Rashi says give him a nice place
amongst these important people, he's a very wealthy person. אתא משאחריני, ata
mishachrini, another person came. אמר להו, amar lehu, so he said to
his servants, פנו מקום לבן מאתיים מנה. pnu makom l'ven matayim maneh.
He thought that this second guy... So
apparently, well, he
was רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda הנשיא *Rebbi Yehuda HaNasi*, who's, so he
was
the exilarch and he was pretty wealthy himself, okay, and he was
a political head. So he had a sense, at least we'll see
in a minute based on the way they were dressed or appeared,
so he wanted to show them proper respect. So A, presumably part
of making the declaration was to show them respect, and B, also
it meant that, you know, the way they would, how they would
seat them amongst which type of people they would seat them, how
they would sort of, you know, the honor they would show them.
So אמר לפניו *amar l'fanav*, so somebody said, so said to him
רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי *Rebbi Yishmael b'Rebbi Yosi*, Rebbi, אביו של זה
*aviv shel zeh*, you should know, the father of the first one
who you only called the millionaire, this guy's father יש לו אלף
ספינות בים וכנגדן אלף עיירות ביבשה *yesh lo elef sfinos bayam u'knegdan
elef ayaros bayabasha*, he's really much wealthier, or at least his father's
much wealthier. So he has a thousand, you know, ships out on
the sea and a thousand villages on the dry land. So אמר
לו *amar lo*, so Rebbi said, לכשתגיע אצל אביו *l'ch'shetagia etzel aviv*.
When you get to his father, this
בן בוניס *Ben Bunyas*, so obviously the father, the בוניס *Bunyas* was
the important guy. So he says, when you get to his father
אמור לו *emor lo*, say to his father אל תשגרנו בכלים הללו
לפני *al teshagreno b'cheilim halalu l'fanai*.
When you send your son to come to visit me, the נשיא
*nasi* or whatever, you should dress him in a way that's appropriate
to his wealth, because I misjudged, you know, what his status was
based on the way that he was dressed. So it's quite fascinating.
Now this seems a little inappropriate, right? So focused on how wealthy
somebody is and so on, but you know, first of all, people
are expecting the appropriate honor and you're the נשיא *nasi*, you know,
then you're the one that affords honor, just because I mean you're
the political head, you're wealthy yourself, so you know, part of responsibility
is to give people the honor that is appropriate to them within
the context of the society that you live. But the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* I presume, because of maybe a
little feeling that this seems like a little funny story, moves on
to the next point. It says רבי מכבד עשירים
*Rebbi mechabed ashirim*. Rebbi makes a point, would actually show honor to
wealthy people. רבי עקיבא מכבד עשירים *Rebbi Akiva mechabed ashirim*, Rebbi Akiva
would do this. כדרש רבא Rava: בר מרי *k'darsh Rava bar Mari*,
like Rava bar Mari explicated the verse: ישב עולם לפני אלקים חסד
ואמת מן ינצרהו *yeshav olam lifnei Elokim chesed v'emes man yintzuruhu*.
So the world was settled before God, kindness and truth, now מן
*man* here, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says here means like it's interpreting
more or less like מזון *mazon*, to sustain the world will protect
it. אימתי ישב עולם לפני אלקים בזמן שחסד ואמת מן ינצרהו *emassay
yeshav olam lifnei Elokim bizman shechesed v'emes man yintzuruhu*, when is the
world set before God? When kindness and truth are sort of, you
know,
come forth and sustain people, and that will protect them. Meaning, because
of the wealthy people, they sustain the world with their philanthropy and
maybe also just with the fact that they generate business and therefore,
you know, we have to give them recognition. Now what it could
be, what it actually is alluding to also, is חסד ואמת *chesed
v'emes*. They do חסד *chesed*, kindness, you know, with their צדקה *tzedakah*
and with providing jobs and so on, and אמת *emes* might often
refer to the idea of תורה *Torah*. So it might mean the
sense of, you know, that wealthy people need to be honored also
by the rabbis and by the people that represent תורה *Torah*. So,
you know,
you obviously should not be like this disdain for wealth or for
wealthy people. Obviously, you know, they do tremendous good, especially if they're
supporting ישיבות *yeshivos*, but even if they're not supporting your particular enterprise,
the rabbinic enterprise directly, but they're helping sustain the poor and helping
sustain society. So it could be that the juxtaposition of חסד *chesed*,
well maybe hopefully by your giving them honor, they will become more
helpful for society. But it's an important point because you know sometimes
a focus on religious pursuit can lead to a disdain for material
goods and not only for yourself but also disdain for people who
pursue material wealth. And here it's actually saying the importance of giving
them recognition and the importance that they can do in the world.
So, and I think it is the juxtaposition of חסד ואמת *chesed
v'emes* is part of what's being communicated here. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* gets back to its main point, which is this
idea of תפיסת יד *tfisat yad*. רבה בר בר חנה Rabbah bar
bar Chana אמר *Rabba bar bar Chana amar*, he goes כגון יצא
דמחא חרישא *kegon yatza d'macha charisha*, having nothing to do with the
דרשה *drasha* before, he says, you know, what would be considered to
be a presence would be something even as trivial or maybe this
is a particular reason for this example as the spike for the
plow for like the plowing apparatus. You know, you'd have
like a plow or whatever pull this, I don't even know what
it's called, but anyway pull this apparatus and it'd have a spike
in it and that would make a furrow as it was being
dragged. So just that spike, even if that's being kept in the
barn or kept in the apartment, that gives this owner a presence
and avoids the need of an עירוב eruv *eiruv* for that unit.
So אמר רב Amar Rav, נחמן *amar Rav Nachman*, תנא דבי שמואל
*tana d'vei Shmuel*, we taught in the house of שמואל *Shmuel*, דבר
הניטל בשבת Davar Hanital b'Shabbos אוסר osser, דבר שאינו ניטל בשבת אינו
אוסר Davar she'eino nital b'Shabbos eino osser, *davar hanitil b'Shabbos osser davar
she'eino nitil b'Shabbos eino osser*. Something that is that can be moved
on שבת Shabbos. אוסר, osser meaning it doesn't help to make that
unit considered to be like the presence of the owner and therefore
that unit is now a problem because it's got it's rented out
by this other guy because since this thing that's being kept there
can be removed on שבת. Shabbos So if I'm keeping my suit
in this apartment on שבת Shabbos and I rent out that apartment,
it's not like oh on שבת Shabbos I still have a presence
in that apartment. It's my suit, I could come pick up my
suit, there's nothing that gives me this ongoing you know presence in
that apartment.
But yes, but if I'm keeping a rock there if I'm keeping
some cash there or if I'm keeping some you know electronic equipment
there דבר שאינו ניטל בשבת nital b'Shabbos אינו אוסר, eino osser, if
I've got stuff there I can't move then that unit does not
create a problem. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, יש לו טבל
ויש לו אששיות, Yesh lo tevel v'yesh lo ashshiyos, if he has
you know grain that has not had תרומות terumos and מעשרות maasros
taken or glass objects וכל דבר שאינו ניטל בשבת, v'chol davar she'eino
nital b'Shabbos, as long as it's something that can't be removed therefore
אינו אוסר, eino osser, then that unit does not yeah like it
would be considered מוקצה מחמת חסרון כיס, muktzah machmas chisron kis, then
it would be considered you know then then that unit would not
create a problem. So the exact parameters you know and there's a
lot of contemporary תשובות teshuvos about this but as I said this
is extremely important because a lot of these cases like I said
hotels, ships, apartment buildings, you know they could be in places where
there's no עירוב eruv and you and very often you don't need
an עירוב eruv because particularly in places where they could actually move
you. This idea of דבר הניטל בשבת you know or אינו ניטל
בשבת eino nital b'Shabbos is if basically you have specific rights to
this unit but it's considered like the owner is still present. But
in certain cases where they can just basically say we need this
unit we're moving you to a better room or whatever it is
you know in a hotel or something then you really have no
sort of real you know like fundamentally it's the other it's the
hotel's room it's not your room even for this time period. But
in an apartment building often it is the major appliances is enough
to obviate the need of an עירוב eruv really make it that
it's all really one owner not multiple owners.
I'm moving all the furniture and the bed in the hotel.
Yeah but you don't have to worry about whether it's ניטל בשבת
nital b'Shabbos or not ניטל בשבת is all I'm saying. Okay so
let's take a look now at the next משנה. mishna. Now I've
said that in the previous משנה mishna the thing that was important
for an עירוב eruv was that it be a domicile. תוספות Tosafos
points out that it's not necessary that somebody be actively living there
to put the עירוב eruv in it. But in terms of the
flip of that that a domicile a separate domicile creates a problem
and has to be a participant in the עירוב eruv and is
אוסר makes it a problem if he doesn't participate that's only or
might only be if there's actually somebody actively living there. And that's
what this משנה mishna comes to address. המניח ביתו והלך לשבות בעיר
אחרת, Hamaniach beiso v'halach lishbos b'ir acheres,
you left your house and you went to spend שבת Shabbos in
another city אחד נכרי ואחד ישראל, Echad nochri v'echad Yisrael, whether a
Jew or a non-Jew הרי זה אוסר דברי רבי מאיר. Harei zeh
osser divrei Rabbi Meir. That's still a problem. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says even with the owner not having an active presence
his domicile in this חצר chatzer requires participation in the עירוב Eruv,
even if there's no active presence of that of the owner. רבי
יהודה אומר אינו אוסר. Rabbi Yehuda omer eino osser. No, if you're
not present it's not a problem. You have to actively be present.
רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yosei omer, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei in principle
agrees with רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda but he says it makes a
difference. נכרי אוסר ישראל אינו אוסר. Nochri osser Yisrael eino osser. A
non-Jew is a problem because even if a non-Jew left a non-Jew
can always come back on שבת Shabbos. you know get on a
get in his car get on his donkey or whatever so the
non-Jew can always come back unannounced whereas a Jew is not going
to travel back on שבת. Shabbos. So it is true it goes
by the sense of a presence but as long as you have
essentially the possibility the potential presence the person might be coming back
that's enough to create a problem and that would be true about
a non-Jew שאין דרך ישראל לבוא בשבת she'ein derech Yisrael lavo b'Shabbos
that a Jew will not normally return on שבת. Shabbos Presumably even
if he's within the תחום techum and in theory could come back
it is very unusual and therefore it's not concerned like he's imminently
present. So that's what he says you don't have to be physically
present but you have to be imminently present. רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi
Shimon omer, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says אפילו הניח ביתו והלך לשבות
אצל בתו, afilu hiniach beiso v'halach lishbos etzel bito,
he basically agrees with רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei and is and is
clarifying.
He says even if the ישראל Yisrael did not go to another
city even if he just went to spend שבת Shabbos by his
daughter באותה העיר, b'osah ha'ir, married daughter in that city even so
even if he's really just totally within the same city אינו אוסר,
he's not considered to be a presence in that house his original
house שכבר הסיח מלבו, shekvar hisiyach milibo, he's already like removed it
from his head he's not spending שבת Shabbos in his home he's
spending שבת Shabbos. with his daughter. So even if he just lives
like a few blocks away it's considered to be that he is
not present in his house for שבת. Shabbos Okay, so רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says I don't care if the person is present if
they've got a house in the חצר chatzer it's a problem. רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says he has to be present. And the last
two opinions said doesn't have to be physically present has to be
what I would call like imminently present or virtually present but if
so that's not the case by a Jew who has left the
house even if he's only a few blocks just to spend שבת
Shabbos, with his daughter, he's going to stay there for שבת, Shabbos.
he's not coming back. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, אמר
רב, Rav, הלכה כרבי שמעון. Halacha k'Rabbi Shimon. We rule like רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon that even if he just went to spend it
in the same city with his daughter, he's not considered present in
his house. ודווקא בתו, V'davka bito, but that's only if he's spending
it with his daughter. אבל בנו, Aval b'no, if he's spending it
with his married son, לא, lo, then he's not necessarily not coming
back. He might have to, he might wind up coming back on
שבת. Shabbos, Why? דאמרי אינשי, D'amrei inshi, because people say, נבח בך
כלבא, navach bach kalba, oh, if a dog is barking at you,
a male dog, you can still go into the house. But נבח
בך גורייתא, navach bach guryata, if a female dog is barking at
you, פוק, poke, you better get out of the house. Which basically
means, right, that's the
son-in-law daughter-in-law, it's assuming that he might not be getting along with
his, with you know, his
child's spouse. So saying if you're going to your son's house, so
your daughter-in-law is, you're getting into a fight with, you'd better then
it's more likely he'll want to leave. Whereas if it's only his
daughter's house, it's only his son-in-law he's getting into a fight with,
he's not going to feel as much of a necessity to leave.
So you can decide for yourself if this is sexist and in
which direction and if it's accurate or not.
What? That's not accurate at all. Thank you, Rip. That was,
I was expecting a comment about, about a sexist perspective, but I
was wondering about the dog issue also.
All right, but what I want to ask you is the concept
someone because in his mind he's not there for שבת, Shabbat, where
else do we see,
not just in his mind, the reality is
I'm not, that's not my house.
Right, he's not living, he's not actively living here.
So so it's like doing ביטול חמץ. bitul Chametz.
Yeah, I mean look, let's remind ourselves that basically in this whole
idea of עירוב, Eruv you've got an idea that it's all רשות
היחיד. reshut hayachid. It's all surrounded by a wall. The only reason
the Rabbis required this עירוב Eruv. was because in, even though halachically
it's all רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid, in sort of, in practice, experientially
or whatever, they're different domains. There's those separate individual units owned by
different people and a shared space owned by everybody and you want
to make that a coherent space. And you are making it a
coherent space, everybody else is joining together. Right? So the question is,
the fact that you technically own a space, but if you don't
have a presence there for שבת, Shabbat. then it doesn't consider, you
know, that that doesn't create a problem because it's not like you're
an outlier and it's not like you have a separate presence separate
from everybody else. I, it makes a lot of sense because you
know, halachically it already is one unified space, it's all one רשות
היחיד. reshut hayachid. It's at the sort of experiential level that they
are distinguished in terms of use and practice, so I think it
makes a lot of sense that if you're actually not actively there
that it's sort of irrelevant to the concerns of the עירוב. eruv.
Do every week we have to rethink?
Unless you do it once. Yeah, but like, you know, unless, but
you can do it once if it's something that doesn't spoil, like
we do it with the box of מצות, matzos, and everybody joins
in. Right, but we also already talked about you can do it
for other people. So you know everybody at the year could pay,
you know, could pay what's it called, like dues to the, and
and I will be the one who will take the responsibility each
week to take some of that money and buy a new loaf
of bread. I mean you can hopefully figure out ways to do
it in a more efficient way. All right, let's take a look
at the next משנה. mishna. Now that was a fun little break,
but now we get back to competing space. But at least this
next case is a little bit more about issues like מחיצות mechitzas
and walls and less about like, you know, just the competing space
itself. בור שבין שתי חצרות, Bor she-bein shtei chatzeirot,
you have a well between two courtyards. אין ממלאין ממנו בשבת, Ein
memalin mimenu b'Shabbat,
you cannot fill from it on שבת. Shabbat, אלא אם כן עשו
לו מחיצה גבוהה עשרה
טפחים. Ella im ken asu lo mechitza gevoha asara t'fachim. Good God,
is this marker working?
I don't know what happened here. Somebody tried to erase it and
anyway. So you basically have your two courtyards. How did this red
become...
anyway, always a problem with markers. It's really bad. Anyway, all right.
You have your two courtyards and you've got each one has a
wall, that's awful, I can't even show that. All right. And we
don't have Balca here. Anyway, so you've got your two courtyards like
this, there's another board here. Okay.
You've got your two courtyards, right? And, and oops, you've got your
two courtyards and each one of them is walled, okay, completely walled.
And then right here in the middle you've got a well that
sits, all right, well, that's not being dangerous. Anyway, imagine you have
a line here and you have this surrounded by walls, this is
surrounded by walls, they're totally surrounded by walls, they share a middle
wall, okay? That's the story. Right in the middle of the middle
wall, you've got a well, right? Well, it goes under. Okay. So,
can you... now the wall sort of runs over the well on
the top, but you know, the well is down on the bottom,
that doesn't prevent access.
Wall suspended in the middle of the well. Can you see the
well?
Yeah, there is a, no, the wall goes over the well. This
is your well, the wall goes over the well. Alright, whatever. Anyway,
so you've got your well here that's got this wall over it,
and and on each side is a walled courtyard. So can you
lower your bucket on your courtyard and draw water from the well?
And the problem is, is that if you're drawing water from the
well, you're also getting water that's from the other
side of the wall and in part from the other courtyard, and
essentially you're transferring objects from one courtyard to another courtyard; you haven't
made an עירוב.
Okay, so the wall wasn't going all the way down. The wall
is going over the well, not only down. Yeah, right. So that's
how we start with. And then the question is, can you make
a wall in the well that effectively creates a sense of separating
the well itself? Okay, so בור שבין שתי חצרות, Bor shebein shtei
chatzerot, אין ממלאין ממנו בשבת, ein memalin mimenu beShabbat, you can't fill
it up from it on שבת, Shabbos אלא אם כן עשו לו
מחיצה גבוהה עשרה טפחים, ela im kein asu lo mechitzah gevohah asarah
tefachim, you have to make a מחיצה mechitzah in the well itself,
ten טפחים tefachim high, בין מלמטה בין מתוך אוגנו, bein milmata bein
mitoch ogno, whether lower or whether right at the lip. So effectively
I mean we'll discuss in the גמרא Gemara what that means, but
assume that this is right this is one of the sides of
the wall and this is your מחיצה mechitzah and here's where the
water level starts and here's where the ground level is. So מלמטה
milmata means you do it right here right by the edge of
the water and מתוך אוגנו mitoch ogno at the lip means you
do it up here but you do some ten מחיצה mechitzah wall
inside of the well. If it's inside the well the water's still
the water's... That's what the גמרא Gemara is going to ask. So
we'll see different opinions in the גמרא Gemara about this but I
gave you one reading of this. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel omer, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
says it's a debate of בית שמאי Beit Shammai and בית הלל.
Beit Hillel. בית שמאי אומרים מלמטה, Beit Shammai omrim milmata, that's that
it has to be below. ובית הלל אומרים מלמעלה, uBeit Hillel omrim
milmala, it can even be above. So presumably that opinion doesn't matter
above or below he says no בית שמאי Beit Shammai demands that
it be below. And now I've given you one version of below,
near the water or near the lip, but the גמרא Gemara. will
give two reads of that. אמר יהודה לא תהא מחיצה גדולה מן
הכותל שביניהם, Amar Yehuda lo tehei mechitzah gedolah min hakotel shebeineihem, and
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says he says why do you need a
what do you call it? Why why do you need a wall
inside the well? You've got this מחיצה mechitzah right you've got this
מחיצה mechitzah that goes over the well at ground level that's enough
to signify that the well is divided between the courtyards. There's no
point of adding a מחיצה mechitzah inside of the well. Okay so
let's take a look first at the opinions of what above and
below means. So גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רב הונא למטה
למטה ממש למעלה למעלה ממש וזה וזה בבור. Amar Rav Huna: lamata,
lamata mamash; lemala, lemala mamash; vezeh vezeh babor. So below means below
near the water level, above means above and they're both inside of
the well. So they're both it's not above ground we already have
a wall above ground, they're both inside of the well but one
means near the water and one means near the lip. רב יהודה
אמר לא למטה למטה מן המים, Rav Yehuda amar lo, lamata lamata
min hamayim, below means in the water itself. למעלה למעלה מן המים,
lemala lemala min hamayim, and above means above the water. So basically
according to the first opinion above means here and below means here,
and according to the second opinion below means in the water and
above means over the water and right next to it. So the
second version's of above is the first version's of below. Okay now
the issue of in the water, רשי Rashi says it means actually
starting at the ground of the of the well and going all
and building up from the actual floor of the well. תוספות Tosafot
says no no no it's not going that far you just have
to be fully in the water but it can be like at
the top of the water it doesn't have to be at the
bottom of the water. Okay so we'll work with תוספות's Tosafot assumption.
Alright so those are the different opinions about what above and below
mean. Now the גמרא's Gemara eventually going to ask what ריף Rif
asks what good is this wall doing? It's no matter in any
of those scenarios the water is still getting through above or below
and the basic answer will be you're right, it's all symbolic. It's
a way of symbolically designating it as if the water is different
on each side but in practice it's not really preventing the water
from flowing from one side to the other. So let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara אמר ליה רבה בר בר חנה לרבא,
Amar lei Rabbah bar bar Chana lerava, so רבה בר בר חנה
said to רבא: Rava הא דאמר רב יהודה למטה למטה מן המים,
ha de'amar Rav Yehuda: lamata, lamata min hamayim, so when he says
below means in the water itself, מאי שנא למטה ממש? mai shna
lamata mamash? Why does he want it to be in the water
itself? How is in the water better than being above the water?
דלא? Dlo? Why why so why why does saying למטה lamata meaning
below in the well but not in the water, it's funny they
call it למטה ממש, lamata mamash, why is that not good? דעריזי
מיא? de'arizei maya? Because you know what good is it if because
that opinion would say that it's not good enough to be above
the water because then the water you know is not dist- is
not differentiated below. So למטה מן המים נמי? lamata min hamayim nami?
So even if it's in the water, הא עריזי מיא? ha arizei
maya? The water still you know is undifferentiated either below it right
if it's in the beginning part of the water, the water still
flows below it or according to רשי Rashi that it's at the
ממש mamash floor of the well, the water still flows above it.
So what good does it do sticking it in the water? The
water still mixes up. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said מאי טעמא
הרי זה מיא *mai ta'ama harei ze maya*. אמר ליה amar lei,
*amar lei*, so he said back to him, לא lo, שמיע לך
הא דאמר רב יהודה Reb Yehuda. אמר רב *lo shemiya lach ha
de'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav*, did you not hear what רב יהודה
Reb Yehuda *Rav Yehuda* said in the name of רב *Rav* ומתנה
משמיה דרבי חייא *u-matna meshmiya de-Rabbi Chiyya* and the you know something
and whatever and it's from the name of רבי חייא *Rabbi Chiyya*?
צריך שיראו ראשו קנים למעלה מן המים טפח tefach *tzarich she-yiru rosho
kanim l'mala min hamayim tefach* that actually the water has to the
the the מחיצה mechitza *mechitza* has to stick out a טפח *tefach*
from the water. So the way רש''י Rashi *Rashi* means this, according
to רש''י Rashi *Rashi* this is a huge demand. You've got this
deep well, you need this מחיצה mechitza *mechitza* to go all the
way from the bottom, go all through the water and come up
and protrude above the water line a טפח *tefach*. It needs to
be a really big מחיצה mechitza *mechitza*, but that answers the question,
isn't the water mixing up from the two sides? And the answer
is no, actually it's going the entire height of the water. תוספות
Tosafos *Tosfos* says it doesn't mean that. תוספות Tosafos *Tosfos* says no,
it just means that mostly in the water, it's mostly in the
water and a little bit appears above, and the fact that a
little bit appears above is enough to get it for this היכר
*heker* idea. That yes, in practice, it's not stopping the water from
mixing. But in terms of what we need to symbolize a division,
it has to be in the water to symbolize we're dividing the
water and it has to protrude out of the water so it
serves as a visual symbol. If it's all in the water it
doesn't do us too much good. Okay, so it doesn't really directly
answer the question that the waters mix up, but it effectively says
it doesn't matter that the waters mixed, it's serving as a good
symbolic division that it's basically in the water and a little bit
protruding and you can see it. According to רש''י Rashi *Rashi*, it
actually is the entire height of the water and it really is
preventing the water from mixing. Such a nice way sticking to my
side? What? Once we made this עירוב *eruv*, are you sticking to
your side? Yes, and then of course you have to stick to
your side. That's the whole point. What if the well what if
the bucket flows or whatever, how much do you have to be
חושש *choshesh* for that? That's not spelled out. Presumably, if it does
flow it is it is a problem. We'll see about that something
like that in a minute. Yes, what was that principle? גוד אסיק
*gud asik*? גוד אסיק *gud asik*, yes. גוד אסיק *gud asik* and
גוד אחית *gud achit*. Yeah, you imagine the wall continuing down. So
we're going to discuss that in a minute. Clearly those that say,
you know, above, you know, it's not in the waterline itself, imagine
that it continues, you know, the idea that we view it as
if it continues down is present, for sure, is part of what's
going on here. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like
this. ותו *v'tu*, so he says wait, I'm still not done. הא
דאמר רב יהודה Reb Yehuda למעלה למעלה מן המים *ha de'amar Rav
Yehuda l'mala l'mala min hamayim*, according to the opinion that above meant
not by the lip of the well, but it meant right above
the water level, so מאי שנא למעלה ממש דלא *mai shna l'mala
mamash d'lo*? This is a question you understand. Why right by the
lip of the well is it not good? דהרי מיא *de-harei maya*,
because if it's at the lip of the well, the water still
mixes below it. So למעלה מן המים נמי הרי מיא *l'mala min
hamayim nami harei maya*. So what? So if it's also lower in
the well and it's above the water level, the water also mixes
below it. So אמר ליה *amar lei*, so this is לא שמיע
לך הא דתני יעקב קרכינאה *lo shmiya lach ha de-tani Yaakov Karchina*,
have you not heard what יעקב קרכינאה *Yaakov Karchina*, one means like
the bald one, צריך שישקע ראשו קנים במים טפח *tzarich she-yishka rosho
kanim bamayim tefach*. No, when we say above the water level, it
still has to dip a little bit into the water. So that
actually you understand why that makes a difference. He's saying I don't
like it up here, because up here it doesn't symbolize a division
of the water. I want it to be down here, but not
just down here, down here and dipping a little bit into the
water. And that will then symbolize a division of the water. Okay,
so those are the that's the version that you need it to
be fully in the water or a little bit in the water,
as opposed to the version that says it can be near the
lip or near the bottom before the water level. Okay, ואלא הא
דאמר רב יהודה Reb Yehuda *ve'ela ha de'amar Rav Yehuda*. That which
רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* said, קורה kora ארבע מתרת בחורבה matarat be-chorva,
*kora arba matira be-churba*. If you have a קורה *kora*, if you
have a beam, okay, it allows it is considered to be in
dry land as a wall. Now there's you know this the reason
this works, I'll give you תוספות Tosafos *Tosfos* explanation is a principle
you might have heard of before called פי תקרה pi tikra יורד
וסותם *pi tikra yored v'soteim*. The lip of a ceiling is like
it goes down. Normally, this is a little bit, I know, sort
of ironic. If you have a wall suspended more than three טפחים
tefachim *tefachim* off the ground, we say if it's more than three
טפחים tefachim. *tefachim*, it's not לבוד *lavud*, it's no good. You don't
say גוד אחית *gud achit*, it goes down because more than three
טפחים tefachim *tefachim* removed, it's not functioning as a wall. You need
it to be actually on the ground itself. Yeah, exactly, גדיד *gadid*.
So you need it to be actually on the ground itself. The
exception to this rule is the idea of when you're having a
virtual wall by the basis of a ceiling. Maybe somehow the ceiling
more communicates an idea that the walls associated with it are not
necessarily just about keeping things out, but you know, somehow creates more
of a virtual house and therefore allows those walls to be more
meaningful even though they don't effectively keep things out. But whatever the
explanation is, if you've got a ceiling and it's basically defined as
a ceiling, this is the way תוספות Tosafos *Tosfos* explains it, by
being ארבע *arba* טפחים tefachim *tefachim* wide and also the edges of
it are straight, are smooth and straight, you view it as though
the edge goes down and it makes a wall. Now can you
say it for all four sides? Can you say it for one
side and the other side has walls? That's a debate how many
walls you can imagine come out of this virtual ceiling. But that's
the principle. And the as I said... And the irony is that
this, which doesn't even really start as a wall, is more effective
because it allows it to work even though there's no real wall
connected to the bottom. Normally we need a real wall connected to
the bottom. So that's what ר' יהודה Reb Yehuda says. If you
have a beam which is four טפחים tefachim wide so it functions
as a ceiling, מתרת בחורבה, it will allow you to carry in
dry land if you're underneath the beam.
Because if you're underneath the beam, if you say פי תקרה pi
tikra on
all sides of the beam, it's like you have four walls.
Or maybe רש"י Rashi imagines maybe the beam is connecting two walls,
so the פי תקרה pi tikra.
gives you the other two. So that's the principle of פי תקרה.
pi tikra, ורב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה, ve-Rav Nachman amar Rabbah
bar Avuha, and ורב נחמן Rav Nachman says in the name of
רבה בר אבוה, Rabbah bar Avuha, now on פ"ו ע"ב, pe vov
amud bet, קורה ארבעה מתרת במים, kora arba matarat bemayim, that the
same it would also work in the water. So here you have,
you have your well, this is your well between the two courtyards,
and you are going to, instead of making a מחיצה Mechitza in
the well, you're going to put a beam over the well. Or
actually maybe it's better like this, a beam over the well like
this. Imagine that's the... fine. Well imagine the courtyards are on these
two sides and you're going to put a beam over the well.
So this beam based on the same principle of פי תקרה, pi
tikra which works better than מחיצות, mechitzas, as I've said, this beam
is going to divide the well and let each side use the
well. תוספות actually also says that the case could be that you've
got this well is... well, we'll just leave it like that. So
he says, הא קאזלי דלי לאידך גיסא? ha k'azli dlei le-idach gisa?
So the גמרא Gemara is not bothered by the idea that it
works better than the wall. As I said, פי תקרה pi tikra
works better than the wall. But it's better by the practical question
which says, fine, this is more effective than a normal wall, it's
like a wall goes down through the well. But you've got your
bucket, you lower it here and it's going to float over to
the other side. If you've got an actual wall in the well,
that wall will hopefully keep the bucket straight. But you've got no
actual wall at all here, you just got an imaginary one. So
isn't the bucket going to float over to the other side? So
the גמרא Gemara says, ומייתי u-maisi and you'll draw water from the
other side? So קימו להו לרבנן, kimu lehu lerabbanan, no, the rabbis
have determined דאין דלי מהלך יותר מארבעה טפחים תחת הקורה, de-ein dlei
mehalach yoter me-arba tefachim tachat hakora, that it won't go more than
four טפחים. tefachim Normally the bucket, since the קורה itself is four
טפחים tefachim wide, the bucket won't go... the beam is more than...
usually the bucket will not go more than four טפחים tefachim? off
of the vertical and therefore it will always stay behind the wall,
the wall of the other edge of the beam. All right. מי
לא מערבי מיא? mi la me-arvaya maya? So the גמרא Gemara says,
but big deal, in practice the water is mixed below and we've
raised the issue above that at least symbolically you're somehow supposed to
divide the water by having the מחיצה Mechitza go into it somewhat,
at least according to one opinion. So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא
משום דקלקלו שהקלו חכמים במים. ela mishum de-kalkulu she-hikilu hachamim bamayim. All
right, so it's a leniency, so sometimes we have special leniencies by
water. Now here's an important הלכה halachic question how to read this.
תוספות reads it like fine, we're more lenient by the beam than
we are by the water. By the water we require it to
go in the well itself, maybe into the water itself, everything we
discussed. By the beam, because this idea of פי תקרה about a
roof, we're more lenient and we don't require it actually to go
into the water itself. So basically there's a difference between the beam
and the wall. רש"י Rashi more significantly להלכה le-halacha reads it as,
oh, you're right. So since the beam works, obviously that opinion that
we said of ר' יהודה that the wall has to go into
the water is not how we פסקן pasken like, because you see
from the beam we don't require to go into the water. So
obviously the פסק psak is like the other opinion that it's enough
that the wall be in the well but it doesn't have to
go into the water and it's actually a פסק psak issue. And
that's very important, going to read a few more lines and discuss
how this was a very relevant פסק psak for the ראשונים. Rishonim.
So let's take a look. אלא משום דקלקלו שהקלו חכמים במים. ela
mishum de-kalkulu she-hikilu hachamim bamayim. כדבעי מיניה ר' טבלא מרב, ke-de-bayei minei
Rabbi Tavla me-Rav, like ר' טבלא Rabbi Tavla asked רב, מחיצה תלויה
מה שתתרי בחורבה? mechitza tluyah mah she-tatrei be-chorva? Again, what I said,
you have a suspended wall that doesn't reach the ground. Normally that's
no good. If it's not within three of the ground and it
works not as well as the roof. If it's not within three
of the ground, it's not a good wall. And he said, will
it work? And he said, אמר ליה, אין מחיצה תלויה מתרת אלא
במים. ein mechitza tluyah tateret ela bemayim. No, this only works by
water. Why is it work more by water? קלקלו שהקלו חכמים במים,
kalkulu she-hikilu hachamim bamayim, because the rabbis were more lenient by water.
Where do we see it working by water? Well one is in
our case of the well, you've got the wall somewhat inserted into
the well and it's considered to go a wall all the way
down. But the more common case is, or the one the גמרא
Gemara more often refers to is, you've got this little platform at
the side of your boat or balcony above a body of water
and you want to draw water and how do you draw water?
You make a booth around it and we've discussed this yesterday and
it's like those walls go down to the water. How are you
allowed to do that? Normally a suspended מחיצה Mechitza doesn't work. Fine,
they're more lenient when it comes to getting access to water. That's
what you see. Now... According to the way רש״י *Rashi* reads this,
the conclusion therefore is, תוספות *Tosafot* reads it that it's just a
conclusion about a leniency about a בירא *bira* that that has a
special set of הלכות *halachos* about the roof as opposed to the
walls. But רש״י *Rashi* reads it even by the walls it's a
leniency and we rule that the walls can be completely above the
water, they don't have to be near the waterline. This is very
important because if they were four טפחים tefachim *tefachim* wide, right, this
wall? No, no, it's the beams that have to be four טפחים
*tefachim* wide to be considered to be a roof. That's what okay.
Now if we take a look at תוספות *Tosafot* קלהו שהקלו חכמים
במים *Kalhu shehikelu chachamim b'mayim*, he talks about a very relevant application.
He says, פירש בקונטרס דלית ליה לרב יהודה *Pireish bakuntres d'leis lei
l'Rav Yehuda*, we don't rule like רב יהודה'ס Reb Yehuda's *Rav Yehuda's*
read that it has to be touching the water or fully in
the water, אלא Ella כרב הונא דבית הלל למעלה מאמה שכאמרי *ella
k'Rav Huna d'Beis Hillel l'mala m'amah sheka'amrei*, that we go like רב
הונא'ס *Rav Huna's* version that it could be really literally fully above
the water, it could be in the well itself but fully above
the water. ועל זה סומכין העולם *V'al zeh somchin ha'olam*, this is
what people rely on, שיש להם בתי כסאות על המים *sheyesh lahem
batei kisa'os al hamayim*, that they have bathrooms that are over the
water. ואף על פי שאין מחיצות מגיעות עד המים *Ve'af al pi
she'ein mechitzos magios ad hamayim*, even though the walls don't get to
the water. Basically what they would do is they would have it
at the edge of the river and they would actually have an
outhouse at the edge of the river. Now you know why there
was so much disease in the Middle Ages because people were I'm
serious, they were pooping right in the river, and they had an
outhouse and the hole in it and the hole went right into
the river. So basically תוספות *Tosafot* says because what we're going to
do is we're going to use the walls of the outhouse as
the walls and view it as going down and we don't need
it to even touch the water and we're fine. Then תוספות *Tosafot*
questions whether that's really good enough because he says those walls are
made for privacy, they're not made to serve as the walls to
effectively to symbolically go into the water, and he questions whether that
would be enough or not. But here is the really relevant issue
of when we say the walls go into the water virtually, do
they have to touch the water or can they be totally suspended
above? How we read this debate in the משנה Mishnah *Mishna*. And
also תוספות'ס *Tosafot's* question about what type of walls do they have
to be made for this purpose. And it's very interesting that a
little slice of life about how they would go to the bathroom
in France and in Germany over those bodies of water. Okay, so
yes I understand that they're so lenient about water because they're living
in the Middle East. Right, תוספות *Tosafot* made that point as well,
excuse the pun, that he says the leniency about water is mostly
about drawing water and getting drinking water. It's not as clear that
these leniencies apply by throwing things into the water. So that's also
another issue that תוספות *Tosafot* raises. Let's continue in the גמרא *Gemara*.
אמר רב יהודה לא תימא מחיצה Mechitza. *Amar Rav Yehuda lo teiman
mechitza* says this divider in the well is not needed, you've already
got a wall running on top of the well. אמר רבה בר
בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן רב יהודה בשיטת רבי יוסי Rebbi Yose
אמרה *Amar Rabba bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan Rav Yehuda b'shitas
Rabbi Yosi amra*. רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* is like רבי יוסי Rebbi
Yose *Rabbi Yosi*, דאמר מחיצה תלויה מתרת אפילו ביבשה *d'amar mechitza tluyah
materes afilu b'yabasha*, because according to רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda*, this wall
is complete, he's using the wall that runs over the water, that's
completely on dry land. And that's similar to רבי יוסי Rebbi Yose
*Rabbi Yosi* who says, although it is seen as going into the
well, to רבי יוסי Rebbi Yose *Rabbi Yosi* who says that a
suspended wall works even on dry land. Which is a רבי יוסי
Rebbi Yose *Rabbi Yosi* that says a minute ago we said a
suspended wall could only work over water, not over land. Where is
this רבי יוסי Rebbi Yose *Rabbi Yosi*? דתנן *Ditnan*, we have a
משנה *Mishna* in סוכה Sukkah, *Sukkah*. המשלשל דפנות *Hamshalshel defanos*, if you
are lowering walls in your building of your סוכה Sukkah. *Sukkah*. למעלה
למטה *L'mala l'mata*, you start at the סכך *schach* and you're building
your walls down, you're lowering a tarp down. בזמן שגבוה מן הארץ
ג' טפחים *Bizman shegavoah min ha'aretz gimmel tefachim*, as long as they
end within three טפחים *tefachim* of the ground. I'm sorry, if they
are three טפחים *tefachim* or higher from the ground, פסולה *psulah*, it's
invalid. למטה למעלה *Mimata l'mala*, if you're building your walls from the
ground up, אם גבוה עשרה טפחים כשרה *im gavoah asara tefachim ksheirah*,
if they're ten טפחים *tefachim* high, it's fine, even if it doesn't
reach the סכך *schach*, because it's easier to extend a wall up
than it is to extend a wall down. That's the תנא קמא
*Tanna Kamma*. רבי יוסי Rebbi Yose. אומר *Rabbi Yosi omer* says, כשם
שלמטה למעלה עשרה *kshem she'lemata l'mala asara*, the same way when you're
going up if you have ten טפחים *tefachim* it's enough, once you
have ten טפחים *tefachim* it's like it extends up and touches the
סכך *schach*, כך למעלה למטה עשרה *kach l'mala l'mata asara*. So similarly
if you're starting מלמעלה למטה *mil'mala l'mata*, when you start by the
סכך *schach* and you work your way down, ten טפחים *tefachim* is
enough and then the rest virtually extends down. So you see that
רבי יוסי Rebbi Yose. *Rabbi Yosi* allows is very lenient always by
suspended walls. And therefore he says even suspended walls over dry land
works and continues down. So the גמרא *Gemara* assumes that that's similar
to the idea that the sort of wall that runs over the
well even if it doesn't go in the well at all it
would be enough to consider it to extend down. And obviously there's
a difference, one relates to water and one relates to dry land,
but the גמרא *Gemara* says this position of רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda*
that you don't need a wall in the well itself is similar
to the position of רבי יוסי Rebbi Yose *Rabbi Yosi* that is
lenient with suspended walls. Let's see what the גמרא *Gemara* says. ולא
היא *V'lo hi*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, no, they're not necessarily
the same position. לא רב יהודה סבר לה כרבי יוסי *Lo Rav
Yehuda savar lah k'Rabbi Yosi*, רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* about the wall
over the well does not necessarily. necessarily agree to רבי יוסי Rebbi
Yose? by סוכה, Sukkah ולא רבי יוסי סבר לה כרב יהודה v'lo
Rebbi Yose savar lah k'Reb Yehuda and רבי יוסי Rebbi Yose doesn't
necessarily hold like רב יהודה. רב יהודה לא סבר לה כרבי יוסי,
Reb Yehuda lo savar lah k'Rebbi Yose, רב יהודה by the well
doesn't necessarily agree by סוכה. Sukkah, עד כאן לא קאמר רב יהודה
אלא בבורות חצירות דרבנן. Ad kan lo ka'amar Rav Yehuda ela beborot
chatzerot derabbanan. When did רב יהודה say that the wall above the
well works? That's only by this whole issue of courtyards, which is
all Rabbinic because it's all a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. תוספות point
out it could also be he said the water aspect is a
reason to be more lenient. תוספות discusses why the גמרא isn't highlighting
that here, but be that as it may, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi
is saying רב יהודה is saying his idea about the wall above
the well by a Rabbinic issue, אלא סוכה דאורייתא, ela Sukkah de'oraisa,
by סוכה Sukkah. where it's a question about the biblical מצוה mitzvah
of סוכה, Sukkah, לא, he would not allow a suspended wall to
work. ולא רבי יוסי סבר לה כרב יהודה v'lo Rebbi Yose savar
lah k'Reb Yehuda and the reverse I could say רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi wouldn't allow רב יהודה'ס case. עד כאן לא קאמר רבי יוסי
אלא בסוכה, Ad kan lo ka'amar Rebbi Yose ela besukkah, when does
רבי יוסי allow a suspended wall? By a סוכה. Sukkah, דאיסור עשה
הוא, De'issur aseihu, at most it's a question of violating a positive
command. אבל שבת דאיסור סקילה הוא, Aval Shabbos de'issur sekila hu, by
שבת Shabbos where although by courtyards it's not a biblical concern, but
you're dealing in an area of הלכה halacha that involves very weighty
transgressions, you're dealing with הלכות שבת hilchos Shabbos that if you actually
transgressed a biblical one would be a capital crime, לא אמר, lo
amar, he would not allow a suspended wall. Now if he's allowing
it by סוכה, Sukkah, he must think that biblically it really works,
but it's even though רבי יוסי thinks that a suspended wall really
works and he allows it by סוכה, Sukkah he might not allow
it by הלכות שבת. hilchos Shabbos. By הלכות שבת hilchos Shabbos we
might want to put on more restrictions. So the גמרא says you
cannot assume that even though both of them are using a suspended
wall, that they both agree with that one would agree with the
other. It could be one area of הלכה halacha is treated as
more weighty than the other area in either direction, and therefore you
would not necessarily say your position both ways. Okay, so now the
גמרא says like this, לא אמר. lo amar. ואי תימא אותו מעשה
נעשה בציפורי Ve'im tomar oso ma'aseh na'asah betzippori now, you're going to
tell me, I'm trying to argue רבי יוסי would only say it
by סוכה, Sukkah he wouldn't say by שבת Shabbos this idea of
suspended walls. But you're going to challenge me, you're going to say
אותו מעשה שנעשה בציפורי, oso ma'aseh she'na'asah betzippori, we know of that
case, there was a famous case in ציפורי, Tzippori, which we'll say
at the end of the דף. daf. Now ציפורי Tzippori was the
city of רבי יוסי.
Okay, and there was a famous case in ציפורי, Tzippori, what happened
there? That we'll find out in a minute that they
basically had to get access to a ספר תורה Sefer Torah and
they made curtains and they carried the ספר תורה Sefer Torah on
שבת Shabbos. because they made an impromptu רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. And
those curtains were suspended more than ten טפחים off the ground. So
and that happened in ציפורי, Tzippori, so presumably that's רבי יוסי. רבי
יוסי was the Rabbi of ציפורי, Tzippori, so you see that רבי
יוסי'ס Rebbi Yose's position by סוכה Sukkah. would be the same position
by שבת. Shabbos, So ואי תימא אותו מעשה שנעשה בציפורי על פי
מי נעשה, ve'im tomar oso ma'aseh shena'asah betzippori al pi mi na'asah,
on whose authority was that done? It clearly לא על פי רבי
יוסי, lo al pi Rebbi Yose, was it not done on the
authority of רבי יוסי? אלא על פי רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי נעשה,
ela al pi Reb Yishmael beRebbi Yose na'asah, it was done by
his son. Okay, so true רבי יוסי was his city, but this
was done maybe he was away for שבת, Shabbos maybe it was
after he passed away. Right, anyway, and this was done by his
son. So it's true his son maybe applied his father's ruling not
only by סוכה Sukkah. but to שבת Shabbos, as well, but the
father might not necessarily have said his הלכה halacha by שבת, Shabbos
might have only said it by סוכה. Okay, now we're going to
find out what that story was. דכי אתא רב דימי אמר, Dechi
asa Rav Dimi amar, when רב דימי Rav Dimi came from ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, he said, פעם אחת שכחו ולא הביאו ספר תורה
מבעוד יום. pa'am achas shachachu velo heviu Sefer Torah mibe'od yom. One
day they forgot to bring the ספר תורה Sefer Torah to the
שול shul on Friday, and it was in somebody's house. למחר, Lemachar,
so what did they do? פירסו סדין על העמודים, parasu sadin al
ha'amudim, they spread a sheet on pillars, they made like an ad
hoc sort of curtains, והביאו ספר תורה, veheviu Sefer Torah, and they
used it to create an ad hoc רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, and
they brought the ספר תורה Sefer Torah to the שול, shul, וקראו
בו, vekaru vo, and they read from it. Okay, now I do
want to say what was the purpose of making the רשות היחיד?
reshus hayachid? First of all, I want to remind you that we
said that walls that are made on שבת Shabbos actually count as
walls. We don't say for הלכות שבת hilchos Shabbos it's not like
you can't change the status of a רשות reshus on שבת Shabbos.
itself, you can. So you would normally think the problem was that
you would have to carry it through I don't know a כרמלית,
karmelis, and therefore you have to turn the כרמלית karmelis into a
רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. רש"י actually says that it's actually addressing a
עירובי חצירות eruvi chatzeros concern, that basically he says, you know, when
you have all of the houses around the courtyard and this space
is a problem, this shared space is a problem because it has
access to... these houses have access to it. So what רש"י says
what you did is, you have your ספר תורה Sefer Torah in
a house here in this courtyard. You had to bring it to
a house in a different courtyard where the שול Shul was. By
making a protected column of sort of pathway surrounded by walls you
blocked access of all the other houses. So you obviated the need
of an עירוב חצרות. Eruv Chatzeiros. Do you understand? So that's what
was happening. No, it wasn't a... no. Oh no, that was another
case maybe but that was not this one. But the point I'm
pointing it out because it's not just that they could use the
walls to make it into a רשות היחיד, Reshus Hayachid, רש"י introduces
the idea they could use the walls to get around the עירוב
חצרות Eruv Chatzeiros problem by blocking the access of the other houses.
Anyway that's what they did and it was suspended walls. So you
see according to רבי יוסי suspended walls work on שבת. Shabbos? Says
no maybe that was his son. And now let's take a look
at this. The גמרא says פרסו לכתחילה מי שרי? Parsu l'chatchila mi
shari? Since when can you make a new wall on שבת? Shabbos
You're not allowed to make a wall on שבת Shabbos? particularly if
the purpose of the wall is to serve as a halakhic wall
to define a new domain. So since when were they allowed to
do this on שבת? Shabbos. והא כל מודים שאין עושין אהל עראי
בשבת. Veha kol modim she'ein osin ohel arai b'Shabbos. Everybody agrees that
you cannot make a temporary אהל Ohel on שבת. Shabbos. And this
is a wall not an אהל Ohel but essentially it's the same
point. You cannot make a new מחיצה on שבת. Shabbos. Again not
for privacy you can. But you can't make a מחיצה to serve
as a halakhic מחיצה on שבת. Shabbos. So how were they allowed
to do this? אלא fine you have to reread it a little
bit. מצאו סדינים פרוסים על עמודים. Matsu sadinim pursim al amudin. They
found like sheets already on pillars and then they sort of moved
the pillars to the sheets. Basically it's like you had a collapsible
מחיצה. You have this curtain hanging on the pillars. It's all folded
up. So they moved it and they spread it and whatever. They
weren't making it new. It was already made and they just situated
it so that it could be effective. והביאו ספר תורה וקראו בה.
Veheivi Sefer Torah vekaru bah. Okay so basically what we have said
now is that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, in the משנה says the
wall above works even without going into the well. That's a suspended
wall. He's lenient at least by the well and by שבת. Shabbos
רבי יוסי says a suspended wall works by סוכה. And the גמרא
is saying at least his son said a suspended wall works even
on dry land and even on שבת Shabbos. by this case of
making this pathway to bring the ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. The only
qualification being they couldn't make the wall לכתחילה l'chatchila because you don't
make a halakhic wall on שבת. Shabbos. Let's just read the next
two lines and we'll pick up with this tomorrow. אמר רבא Amar
Rava so רבא said רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda רבי חנניה בן עקביא
Rabbi Hananya ben Akavya אמרו דבר אחד. amru davar echad. So רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that was so lenient by this wall above the
well and he is similar he and רבי חנניה בן עקביא Rabbi
Hananya ben Akavya essentially say the same thing. So we're basically saying
that there's this other position רבי חנניה בן עקביא Rabbi Hananya ben
Akavya who also is lenient by suspended walls. רבי יהודה הדר אמרין
Rabbi Yehuda hada amrin רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda we just said it.
רבי חנניה בן עקביא. Rabbi Hananya ben Akavya. Now what's רבי חנניה
בן עקביא? Rabbi Hananya ben Akavya? דתניא De-tanya we taught in a
ברייתא. Braisa. רבי חנניה בן עקביא אומר Rabbi Hananya ben Akavya omer
גזוסטרא Gezustra if you have a balcony שיש בה ארבע אמות על
ארבע אמות. she-yeish bah arba amos al arba amos. Four אמות amos
by four אמות. amos. Who knows how many טפחים is four אמות?
amos? Six טפחים to an אמה. amah. Quick do the math: 24
by 24. You have it over the body of water. חוקק בה
ארבע על ארבע וממלא. Chokek bah arba al arba umemalei. So what
he says you can do is: Here's your thing. You make a
four by four טפח exactly in the middle. You do not need
to make walls around it to consider that walls go down to
the ocean. Why don't you? Because if you make four by four
exactly in the middle what do you have on each side? How
many טפחים? If the whole thing is 24. So if you take
the four in the middle you have ten on each side. So
if you have ten on each side he says you view it
as if those ten go down and create four walls. Do you
see what he's saying? So right if you've got this thing in
the middle I can't do it but anyway he said since you've
got ten טפחים on each side you virtually look at it as
if they bang down and make walls. So he says we have
these two opinions that are very lenient about walls seen as extending
down over water on שבת. רבי יהודה the wall over the well
without going into the well and חנניה בן עקביא Hananya ben Akavya
who says even without any walls just with the ability to virtually
bend your platform and turn it into walls that would count enough
to be considered walls to give you access to the water. Okay
so we'll wrap up with this tomorrow. Okay גזוסטרא Gezustra and a
מרפסת? mirpeset? מרפסת? Mirpeset? מרפסת Mirpeset I don't know. גזוסטרא Gezustra is
more like is more like just a plank or some type of
a protrusion that gives you access to the that gives you access
to above water.